Then did Väinämöinen, rising,
Nousi siitä Väinämöinen
Set his feet upon the surface
jalan kahen kankahalle
Of a sea-encircled island,
saarehen selällisehen,
In a region bare of forest.
manterehen puuttomahan.
There he dwelt, while years passed over,
Viipyi siitä vuotta monta,
And his dwelling he established
aina eellehen eleli
On the silent, voiceless island,
saaressa sanattomassa,
In a barren, treeless country.
manteressa puuttomassa.
Then he pondered and reflected,
Arvelee, ajattelevi,
In his mind he turned it over,
pitkin päätänsä pitävi:
"Who shall sow this barren country,
kenpä maita kylvämähän,
Thickly scattering seeds around him?"
toukoja tihittämähän?
Pellervoinen, earth-begotten,
Pellervoinen, pellon poika,
Sampsa, youth of smallest stature,
Sampsa poika pikkarainen,
Came to sow the barren country,
sep' on maita kylvämähän,
Thickly scattering seeds around him.
toukoja tihittämähän!
Down he stooped the seeds to scatter,
Kylvi maita kyyhätteli,
On the land and in the marshes,
kylvi maita, kylvi soita,
Both in flat and sandy regions,
kylvi auhtoja ahoja,
And in hard and rocky places.
panettavi paasikoita.
On the hills he sowed the pine-trees,
Mäet kylvi männiköiksi,
On the knolls he sowed the fir-trees,
kummut kylvi kuusikoiksi,
And in sandy places heather;
kankahat kanervikoiksi,
Leafy saplings in the valleys.
notkot nuoriksi vesoiksi.
In the dales he sowed the birch-trees,
Noromaille koivut kylvi,
In the loose earth sowed the alders,
lepät maille leyhke'ille,
Where the ground was damp the cherries,
tuomet kylvi tuorehille,
Likewise in the marshes, sallows.
raiat maille raikkahille,
Rowan-trees in holy places,
pihlajat pyhille maille,
Willows in the fenny regions,
pajut maille paisuville,
Juniper in stony districts,
katajat karuille maille,
Oaks upon the banks of rivers.
tammet virran vieremille.
Now the trees sprang up and flourished,
Läksi puut ylenemähän,
And the saplings sprouted bravely.
vesat nuoret nousemahan.
With their bloom the firs were loaded,
Kasvoi kuuset kukkalatvat,
And the pines their boughs extended.
lautui lakkapäät petäjät.
In the dales the birch was sprouting,
Nousi koivupuut noroilla,
In the loose earth rose the alders,
lepät mailla leyhke'illä,
Where the ground was damp the cherries,
tuomet mailla tuorehilla,
Juniper in stony districts,
katajat karuilla mailla,
Loaded with its lovely berries;
katajahan kaunis marja,
And the cherries likewise fruited.
tuomehen hyvä he'elmä.
Väinämöinen, old and steadfast,
Vaka vanha Väinämöinen
Came to view the work in progress,
kävi tuota katsomahan
Where the land was sown by Sampsa,
Sampsan siemenen aloa,
And where Pellervoinen laboured.
Pellervoisen kylvämiä.
While he saw the trees had flourished,
Näki puut ylenneheksi,
And the saplings sprouted bravely,
vesat nuoret nousneheksi;
Yet had Jumala's tree, the oak-tree,
yks' on tammi taimimatta,
Not struck down its root and sprouted.
juurtumatta puu Jumalan.
Therefore to its fate he left it,
Heitti herjan valloillensa,
Left it to enjoy its freedom,
olevillen onnillensa;
And he waited three nights longer,
vuotti vielä yötä kolme,
And as many days he waited.
saman verran päiviäki.
Then he went and gazed around him,
Kävi siitä katsomahan
When the week was quite completed.
viikon päästä viimeistäki:
Yet had Jumala's tree, the oak-tree,
ei ole tammi kasvanunna,
Not struck down its root and sprouted.
juurtununna puu Jumalan.
Then he saw four lovely maidens;
Niin näkevi neljä neittä,
Five, like brides, from water rising;
viisi veen on morsianta.
And they mowed the grassy meadow,
Ne oli nurmen niitännässä,
Down they cut the dewy herbage,
kastekorren katkonnassa
On the cloud-encompassed headland,
nenässä utuisen niemen,
On the peaceful island's summit,
päässä saaren terhenisen;
What they mowed, they raked together,
mink' on niitti, sen haravoi,
And in heaps the hay collected.
kaikki karhille veteli.
From the ocean rose up Tursas,
Tulipa merestä Tursas,
From the waves arose the hero,
uros aalloista yleni.
And the heaps of hay he kindled,
Tunki heinäset tulehen,
And the flames arose in fury.
ilmivalkean väkehen;
All was soon consumed to ashes,
ne kaikki poroksi poltti,
Till the sparks were quite extinguished.
kypeniksi kyyetteli.
Then among the heaps of ashes,
Tuli tuhkia läjänen,
In the dryness of the ashes,
koko kuivia poroja.
There a tender germ he planted,
Saip' on siihen lemmen lehti,
Tender germ, of oak an acorn
lemmen lehti, tammen terho,
Whence the beauteous plant sprang upward,
josta kasvoi kaunis taimi,
And the sapling grew and flourished,
yleni vihanta virpi;
As from earth a strawberry rises,
nousi maasta mansikkaisna,
And it forked in both directions.
kasvoi kaksihaarukkaisna.
Then the branches wide extended,
Ojenteli oksiansa,
And the leaves were thickly scattered,
levitteli lehviänsä.
And the summit rose to heaven,
Latva täytti taivahalle,
And its leaves in air expanded.
lehvät ilmoille levisi:
In their course the clouds it hindered,
piätti pilvet juoksemasta,
And the driving clouds impeded,
hattarat hasertamasta,
And it hid the shining sunlight,
päivän peitti paistamasta,
And the gleaming of the moonlight.
kuuhuen kumottamasta.
Then the aged Väinämöinen,
Silloin vanha Väinämöinen
Pondered deeply and reflected,
arvelee, ajattelevi:
"Is there none to fell the oak-tree,
oisko tammen taittajata,
And o'erthrow the tree majestic?
puun sorean sortajata?
Sad is now the life of mortals,
Ikävä inehmon olla,
And for fish to swim is dismal,
kamala kalojen uia
Since the air is void of sunlight,
ilman päivän paistamatta,
And the gleaming of the moonlight."
kuuhuen kumottamatta.
But they could not find a hero,
Ei ole sitä urosta
Nowhere find a man so mighty,
eikä miestä urheata,
Who could fell the giant oak-tree,
joka taisi tammen kaata,
With its hundred spreading branches.
satalatvan langettoa.
Then the aged Väinämöinen,
Siitä vanha Väinämöinen
Spoke the very words which follow;
itse tuon sanoiksi virkki:
"Noble mother, who hast borne me,
"Kave äiti, kantajani,
Luonnotar, who me hast nurtured;
luonnotar, ylentäjäni!
Send me powers from out the ocean:
Laitapa ve'en väkeä
(Numerous are the powers of ocean)
- veessä on väkeä paljo -
So that they may fell the oak-tree,
tämä tammi taittamahan,
And destroy the tree so baneful,
puu paha hävittämähän
That the sun may shine upon us.
eestä päivän paistavaisen,
And the pleasant moonlight glimmer."
tieltä kuun kumottavaisen!"
Then a man arose from ocean,
Nousipa merestä miesi,
From the waves a hero started,
uros aallosta yleni.
Not the hugest of the hugest,
Ei tuo ollut suuren suuri
Nor the smallest of the smallest.
eikä aivan pienen pieni:
As a man's thumb was his stature;
miehen peukalon pituinen,
Lofty as the span of woman.
vaimon vaaksan korkeuinen.
Decked his head a helm of copper,
Vaski- oli hattu hartioilla,
On his feet were boots of copper,
vaskisaappahat jalassa,
On his hands were copper gauntlets.
vaskikintahat käessä,
Gloves adorned with copper tracings;
vaskikirjat kintahissa,
Round his waist his belt was copper;
vaskivyöhyt vyölle vyötty,
In his belt his axe was copper;
vaskikirves vyön takana:
And the haft thereof was thumb-long,
varsi peukalon pituinen,
And the blade thereof was nail-long.
terä kynnen korkeuinen.
Väinämöinen, old and steadfast,
Vaka vanha Väinämöinen
Deeply pondered and reflected:
arvelee, ajattelevi:
"While he seems a man in semblance,
on miesi näkemiänsä,
And a hero in appearance,
uros silmänluontiansa,
Yet his height is but a thumb-length,
pystyn peukalon pituinen,
Scarce as lofty as an ox-hoof."
härän kynnen korkunainen!
Then he spoke the words which follow,
Siitä tuon sanoiksi virkki,
And expressed himself in this wise:
itse lausui, noin nimesi:
"Who are you, my little fellow,
"Mi sinä olet miehiäsi,
Most contemptible of heroes,
ku, kurja, urohiasi?
Than a dead man scarcely stronger;
Vähän kuollutta parempi,
And your beauty all has vanished."
katonutta kaunihimpi!"
Then the puny man from ocean,
Sanoi pikku mies merestä,
Hero of the floods, made answer:
uros aallon vastaeli:
"I'm a man as you behold me,
"Olen mie mokoma miesi,
Small, but mighty water-hero,
uros pieni, veen väkeä.
I have come to fell the oak-tree,
Tulin tammen taittamahan,
And to splinter it to fragments."
puun murskan murentamahan."
Väinämöinen, old and steadfast,
Vaka vanha Väinämöinen
Answered in the words which follow:
itse tuon sanoiksi virkki:
"You have hardly been created,
"Ei liene sinua luotu,
Neither made, nor so proportioned,
eipä luotu eikä suotu
As to fell this mighty oak-tree,
ison tammen taittajaksi,
Overthrow the tree stupendous."
puun kamalan kaatajaksi."
Scarcely had the words been spoken,
Sai toki sanoneheksi;
While his gaze was fixed upon him,
katsahtavi vielä kerran:
When the man transformed before him,
näki miehen muuttunehen,
And became a mighty hero.
uuistunehen urohon!
While his feet the earth were stamping,
Jalka maassa teutaroivi,
To the clouds his head he lifted,
päähyt pilviä pitävi;
To his knees his beard was flowing,
parta on eessä polven päällä,
To his spurs his locks descended.
hivus kannoilla takana;
Fathom-wide his eyes were parted,
syltä oli silmien välitse,
Fathom-wide his trousers measured;
syltä housut lahkehesta,
Round his knee the girth was greater,
puoltatoista polven päästä,
And around his hip 'twas doubled.
kahta kaation rajasta.
Then he sharpened keen the axe-blade,
Hivelevi kirvestänsä,
Brought the polished blade to sharpness;
tahkaisi tasatereä
Six the stones on which he ground it,
kuutehen kovasimehen,
Seven the stones on which he whet it.
seitsemähän sieran päähän.
Then the man stepped forward lightly,
Astua lykyttelevi,
Hastened on to do his mission;
käyä kulleroittelevi
Wide his trousers, and they fluttered
lave'illa lahkehilla,
Round his legs as onward strode he,
leve'illä liehuimilla.
And the first step taken, brought him
Astui kerran keikahutti
To the shore so soft and sandy;
hienoiselle hietikolle,
With the second stride he landed
astui toisen torkahutti
On the dun ground further inland,
maalle maksankarvaiselle,
And the third step brought him quickly,
kolmannenki koikahutti
Where the oak itself was rooted.
juurelle tulisen tammen.
With his axe he smote the oak-tree,
Iski puuta kirvehellä,
With his sharpened blade he hewed it;
tarpaisi tasaterällä.
Once he smote it, twice he smote it,
Iski kerran, iski toisen,
And the third stroke wholly cleft it.
kohta kolmannen yritti;
From the axe the flame was flashing,
tuli tuiski kirvehestä,
Flame was bursting from the oak-tree,
panu tammesta pakeni:
As he strove to fell the oak-tree,
tahtoi tammi kallistua,
Overthrow the tree stupendous.
lysmyä rutimoraita.
Thus the third blow was delivered,
Niin kerralla kolmannella
And the oak-tree fell before him,
jopa taisi tammen kaata,
For the mighty tree was shattered,
ruhtoa rutimoraian,
And the hundred boughs had fallen,
satalatvan lasketella.
And the trunk extended eastward,
Tyven työnnytti itähän,
And the summit to the north-west,
latvan laski luotehesen,
And the leaves were scattered southwards,
lehvät suurehen suvehen,
And the branches to the northward.
oksat puolin pohjosehen.
He who took a branch from off it,
Kenpä siitä oksan otti,
Took prosperity unceasing,
se otti ikuisen onnen;
What was broken from the summit,
kenpä siitä latvan taittoi,
Gave unending skill in magic;
se taittoi ikuisen taian;
He who broke a leafy branchlet,
kenpä lehvän leikkaeli,
Gathered with it love unending.
se leikkoi ikuisen lemmen.
What remained of fragments scattered,
Mi oli lastuja pirannut,
Chips of wood, and broken splinters,
pälähellyt pälkäreitä
On the bright expanse of ocean,
selvälle meren selälle,
On the far-extending billows,
lake'ille lainehille,
In the breeze were gently rocking,
noita tuuli tuuitteli,
On the waves were lightly drifted.
meren läikkä läikytteli
Like the boats on ocean's surface,
venosina veen selällä,
Like the ships amid the sea-waves.
laivasina lainehilla.
Northward drove the wind the fragments,
Kantoi tuuli Pohjolahan.
Where the little maid of Pohja,
Pohjan piika pikkarainen
Stood on beach, and washed her head-dress,
huntujahan huuhtelevi,
And she washed her clothes and rinsed them,
virutteli vaattehia
On the shingle by the ocean,
rannalla vesikivellä
On a tongue of land projecting.
pitkän niemyen nenässä.
On the waves she saw the fragments,
Näki lastun lainehilla;
Put them in her birchbark wallet,
tuon kokosi konttihinsa,
In her wallet took them homeward;
kantoi kontilla kotihin,
In the well-closed yard she stored them,
pitkäkielellä piha'an,
For the arrows of the sorcerer,
tehä noian nuoliansa,
For the chase to furnish weapons.
ampujan asehiansa.
When the oak at last had fallen,
Kun oli tammi taittununna,
And the evil tree was levelled,
kaatununna puu katala,
Once again the sun shone brightly,
pääsi päivät paistamahan,
And the pleasant moonlight glimmered,
pääsi kuut kumottamahan,
And the clouds extended widely,
pilvet pitkin juoksemahan,
And the rainbow spanned the heavens,
taivon kaaret kaartamahan
O'er the cloud-encompassed headland,
nenähän utuisen niemen,
And the island's misty summit.
päähän saaren terhenisen.
Then the wastes were clothed with verdure,
Siit' alkoi salot silota,
And the woods grew up and flourished;
metsät mielin kasvaella,
Leaves on trees and grass in meadows.
lehti puuhun, ruoho maahan,
In the trees the birds were singing,
linnut puuhun laulamahan,
Loudly sang the cheery throstle;
rastahat iloitsemahan,
In the tree-tops called the cuckoo.
käki päällä kukkumahan.
Then the earth brought forth her berries;
Kasvoi maahan marjanvarret,
Shone the fields with golden blossoms;
kukat kultaiset keolle;
Herbs of every species flourished;
ruohot kasvoi kaikenlaiset,
Plants and trees of all descriptions;
monenmuotoiset sikesi.
But the barley would not flourish,
Ohra on yksin nousematta,
Nor the precious seed would ripen.
touko kallis kasvamatta.
Then the aged Väinämöinen,
Siitä vanha Väinämöinen
Walked around, and deeply pondered,
astuvi, ajattelevi
By the blue waves' sandy margin,
rannalla selän sinisen,
On the mighty ocean's border,
ve'en vankan vieremillä.
And six grains of corn he found there,
Löyti kuusia jyviä,
Seven fine seeds of corn he found there,
seitsemiä siemeniä
On the borders of the ocean,
rannalta merelliseltä,
On the yielding sandy margin.
hienoiselta hietiköltä;
In a marten's skin he placed them,
kätki nää'än nahkasehen,
From the leg of summer squirrel.
koipehen kesäoravan.
Then he went to sow the fallows;
Läksi maata kylvämähän,
On the ground the seeds to scatter,
siementä sirottamahan
Near to Kaleva's own fountain,
vierehen Kalevan kaivon,
And upon the field of Osmo.
Osmon pellon penkerehen.
From a tree there chirped the titmouse:
Tirskuipa tiainen puusta:
"Osmo's barley will not flourish,
"Eipä nouse Osmon ohra,
Nor will Kaleva's oats prosper,
ei kasva Kalevan kaura
While untilled remains the country,
ilman maan alistamatta,
And uncleared remains the forest,
ilman kasken kaatamatta,
Nor the fire has burned it over."
tuon tulella polttamatta."
Väinämöinen, old and steadfast,
Vaka vanha Väinämöinen
Ground his axe-blade edge to sharpness
teetti kirvehen terävän.
And began to fell the forest,
Siitä kaatoi kasken suuren,
Toiling hard to clear the country.
mahottoman maan alisti.
All the lovely trees he levelled,
Kaikki sorti puut soreat;
Sparing but a single birch-tree,
yhen jätti koivahaisen
That the birds might rest upon it,
lintujen leposijaksi,
And from thence might call the cuckoo.
käkösen kukuntapuuksi.
In the sky there soared an eagle,
Lenti kokko halki taivon,
Of the birds of air the greatest,
lintunen ylitse ilman.
And he came and gazed around him.
Tuli tuota katsomahan:
"Wherefore is the work unfinished,
"Miksipä on tuo jätetty
And the birch-tree still unfallen?
koivahainen kaatamatta,
Wherefore spare the beauteous birch-tree?"
puu sorea sortamatta?"
Said the aged Väinämöinen,
Sanoi vanha Väinämöinen:
"Therefore is the birch left standing,
"Siksipä on tuo jätetty:
That the birds may perch upon it;
lintujen lepeämiksi,
All the birds of air may rest there."
kokon ilman istumiksi."
Said the bird of air, the eagle,
Sanoi kokko, ilman lintu:
"Very wisely hast thou acted,
"Hyvinpä sinäki laait:
Thus to leave the birch-tree standing
heitit koivun kasvamahan,
And the lovely tree unfallen,
puun sorean seisomahan
That the birds may perch upon it,
linnuille lepeämiksi,
And that I myself may rest there."
itselleni istumiksi."
Then the bird of air struck fire,
Tulta iski ilman lintu,
And the flames rose up in brightness,
valahutti valkeaista.
While the north wind fanned the forest,
Pohjaistuuli kasken poltti,
And the north-east wind blew fiercely.
koillinen kovin porotti:
All the trees were burned to ashes,
poltti kaikki puut poroksi,
Till the sparks were quite extinguished.
kypeniksi kyyetteli.
Then the aged Väinämöinen,
Siitä vanha Väinämöinen
Took the six seeds from his satchel,
otti kuusia jyviä,
And he took the seven small kernels,
seitsemiä siemeniä
From the marten's skin he took them,
yhen nää'än nahkasesta,
From the leg of summer squirrel,
koivesta kesäoravan,
From the leg of summer ermine.
kesäkärpän kämmenestä.
Then he went to sow the country,
Läksi maata kylvämähän,
And to scatter seeds around him,
siementä sirottamahan.
And he spoke the words which follow;
Itse tuon sanoiksi virkki:
"Now I stoop the seeds to scatter,
"Minä kylvän kyyhättelen
As from the Creator's fingers,
Luojan sormien lomitse,
From the hand of Him Almighty,
käen kautta kaikkivallan
That the country may be fertile,
tälle maalle kasvavalle,
And the corn may grow and flourish.
ahollen ylenevälle.
"Patroness of lowland country,
"Akka manteren-alainen,
Old one of the plains; Earth-Mother,
mannun eukko, maan emäntä!
Let the tender blade spring upward,
Pane nyt turve tunkemahan,
Let the earth support and cherish.
maa väkevä vääntämähän!
Might of earth will never fail us,
Eip' on maa väkeä puutu
Never while the earth existeth,
sinä ilmoisna ikänä,
When the Givers are propitious.
kun lie armo antajista,
And Creation's daughters aid us.
lupa luonnon tyttäristä.
"Rise, O earth; from out thy slumber,
"Nouse, maa, makoamasta,
Field of the Creator, rouse thee,
Luojan nurmi, nukkumasta!
Make the blade arise and flourish.
Pane korret korttumahan
Let the stalks grow up and lengthen,
sekä varret varttumahan!
That the ears may grow by thousands,
Tuhansin neniä nosta,
Yet a hundredfold increasing,
saoin haaroja hajota
By my ploughing and my sowing,
kynnöstäni, kylvöstäni,
In return for all my labour.
varsin vaivani näöstä!
"Ukko, thou of Gods the highest.
"Oi Ukko, ylijumala
Father, thou in heaven abiding,
tahi taatto taivahinen,
Thou to whom the clouds are subject.
vallan pilvissä pitäjä,
Of the scattered clouds the ruler,
hattarojen hallitsija!
All thy clouds do thou assemble,
Piä pilvissä keräjät,
In the light make clear thy counsel,
sekehissä neuvot selvät!
Send thou forth a cloud from eastwards
Iätä iästä pilvi,
In the north-west let one gather,
nosta lonka luotehesta,
Send thou others from the westward,
toiset lännestä lähetä,
Let them drive along from southward.
etelästä ennättele!
Send the light rain forth from heaven,
Vihmo vettä taivosesta,
Let the clouds distil with honey,
mettä pilvistä pirota
That the corn may sprout up strongly,
orahille nouseville,
And the stalks may wave and rustle."
touoille tohiseville!"
Ukko, then, of Gods the highest,
Tuo Ukko, ylijumala,
Father of the highest heaven,
taatto taivon valtiainen,
Heard, and all the clouds assembled.
piti pilvissä keräjät,
In the light made clear his counsel,
sekehissä neuvot selvät.
And he sent a cloud from eastward.
Iätti iästä pilven,
In the north-west let one gather,
nosti longan luotehesta,
Others, too, he sent from westward,
toisen lännestä lähetti,
Let them drive along from southward,
etelästä ennätteli;
Linked them edge to edge together,
syrjin yhtehen sysäsi,
And he closed the rifts between them.
lomituksin loukahutti.
Then he sent the rain from heaven,
Vihmoi vettä taivosesta,
And the clouds distilled sweet honey,
mettä pilvistä pirotti
That the corn might sprout up stronger,
orahille kasvaville,
And the stalks might wave and rustle.
touoille tohiseville.
Thus the sprouting germ was nourished,
Nousipa oras okinen,
And the rustling stalks grew upward,
kannonkarvainen yleni
From the soft earth of the cornfield.
maasta pellon pehmeästä,
Through the toil of Väinämöinen.
Väinämöisen raatamasta.
After this, two days passed over,
Jopa tuosta toisna päänä,
After two nights, after three nights,
kahen, kolmen yön perästä,
When the week was full completed,
viikon päästä viimeistäki
Väinämöinen, old and steadfast,
vaka vanha Väinämöinen
Wandered forth to see the progress;
kävi tuota katsomahan
How his ploughing and his sowing
kyntöänsä, kylvöänsä,
And his labours had resulted.
varsin vaivansa näköä:
There he found the barley growing,
kasvoi ohra mieltä myöten,
And the ears were all six-cornered,
tähkät kuuella taholla,
And the stalks were all three-knotted.
korret kolmisolmuisena.
Then the aged Väinämöinen
Siinä vanha Väinämöinen
Wandered on and gazed around him,
katseleikse, käänteleikse.
And the cuckoo, bird of springtime,
Niin tuli kevätkäkönen,
Came and saw the birch-tree growing.
näki koivun kasvavaksi:
"Wherefore is the birch left standing,
"Miksipä on tuo jätetty
And unfelled the slender birch-tree?"
koivahainen kaatamatta?"
Said the aged Väinämöinen,
Sanoi vanha Väinämöinen:
"Therefore is the birch left standing,
"Siksipä on tuo jätetty
And unfelled the slender birch-tree,
koivahainen kasvamahan:
As a perch for thee, O Cuckoo;
sinulle kukuntapuuksi.
Whence the cuckoo's cry may echo.
Siinä kukkuos, käkönen,
From thy sand-hued throat cry sweetly,
helkyttele, hietarinta,
With thy silver voice call loudly,
hoiloa, hopearinta,
With thy tin-like voice cry clearly,
tinarinta, riukuttele!
Call at morning, call at evening,
Kuku illoin, kuku aamuin,
And at noontide call thou likewise,
kerran keskipäivälläki,
To rejoice my plains surrounding,
ihanoiksi ilmojani,
That my woods may grow more cheerful,
mieluisiksi metsiäni,
That my coast may grow more wealthy,
rahaisiksi rantojani,
And my region grow more fruitful."
viljaisiksi vieriäni!"